Murtaza Tamjeed

mt1256@rit.edu linkedin.com/in/murtaza-tamjeed

INTERESTS

Accessibility of Research: I want to make research more accessible. My current project focuses on designing and developing support tools including strategies and software solutions to support researchers with disabilities.

Accessibility and Machine Learning: I investigate accessibility of mobile apps, and bias in machine learning. My current project involves NLP and machine learning techniques to analyze and automate identification of accessibility user reviews for mobile apps. In my subsequent studies, I aim to investigate how NLP models are biased toward disability and in predicting and classifying accessibility-related user reviews.

EDUCATION

Rochester Institute of Technology (RIT) 2024 (Expected)

Ph.D. in Computing and Information Sciences

Advisor: Dr. Kristen Shinohara

Rochester Institute of Technology 2020

Master's in Software Engineering

Thesis Advisor: Dr. Mohammad Wiem Makauer

Kabul University 2013

Bachelor's in Computer Science Thesis Advisor: Dr. Hasan Adelyar

PUBLICATIONS

Usability, Accessibility and Social Entanglements in Advanced Tool Use by Vision Impaired Graduate Students — ACM SIGCHI CSCW2022

under review

Understanding Disability Services Toward Improving Graduate Student Support — ACM SIGACCESS ASSETS21

https://doi.org/10.1145/3441852.3471231

Finding the Needle in a Haystack: On the Automatic Identification of Accessibility User Reviews — ACM CHI 2021

https://doi-org.ezproxy.rit.edu/10.1145/3411764.3445281

Accessible Computing Education in Colleges and Universities — *White Paper* https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/accessible-cs

Accessibility in User Reviews for Mobile Apps: An Automated Detection Approach — *Master's Thesis* https://scholarworks.rit.edu/theses/10511

EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant

AUG 2020 - Present

Center for Accessibility and Inclusion Research (CAIR) Lab

- Leading an NSF-funded research project that aims to improve technology for students with disabilities
- Investigating accessibility and usability of advanced tools used in research by blind and low vision doctoral students

Accessibility Tech Intern

MAY 2022 - AUG 2022

Yahoo!

- With Yahoo's Accessibility and Product Inclusion team, I provide expertise and support in various Yahoo product groups (Yahoo Mail, Yahoo Sports, Yahoo Finance, etc.) to build the products fully accessible.
- Conduct user feedback analysis, user studies, and observations to answer *how accessible Yahoo products are*.

Research Trainee

JAN 2022 - Present

AWARE-AI NSF program at RIT

- Participating in AI-HCI research track and receiving training by Dr. Huenerfauth and Dr. Shinohara
- Participating in lab rotations, grant writing, workshops, seminars, and talks

Lead Software Developer

Tetra Tech

MAR 2015 - AUG 2018

- Led a team of developers for development and growth of Afghanistan's Criminal Management System
- As a full-stack LAMP developer, I was responsible for the development and modification of new and existing functionality to the system using PHP MVC CodeIgniter framework
- Developed dynamic dashboards that reduced up to 50% report generating time for system users
- Successfully redesigned the user interface of the system by integrating Bootstrap
- Developed all code in accordance with relevant accessibility guidelines

Software Developer ADRAS

FEB 2013 - JAN 2015

- Collaborated with teams of developers, designers, and project managers for the development and growth of Afghanistan's National Information Management System
- Designed and coded various features and modules for the system and evaluated with system users

Computer Science Lecturer

Kabul University

MAR 2014 - AUG 2018

- Taught HCl Foundations, Foundations of Software Engineering, Algorithms, and Data Analysis
- Advised and mentored senior students with their research and capstone projects

Senior Lecturer (Part-time)

APR 2014 - FEB 2015

Khatam-ul-Nabieen University

- Taught C# and CS Foundation courses
- Advised and mentored senior students with their research and capstone projects

GRUDUATE-LEVEL COURSES

Qualitative Research Methods	Cyberinfrastructure Foundation
Research Foundations (Quant)	Quantitative Foundations
Foundations of HCI	Foundation of Data Science
Engineering Accessible Software	Software Architecture
Software Evolution and Reengineering	Process Engineering
Software Quality Engineering	Software Modeling
Visual Analytics	Creative Critical Thinking

SCHOLARSHIPS & AWARDS

Ph.D. Merit Scholarship - Rochester Institute of Technology

Financial Support for Ph.D. Studies

Fulbright Foreign Student Program - U.S. Department of State

Prestigious Scholarship - Full coverage for earning master's in the United States

ITEC (Indian Technical and Economic Cooperation)

Full support for pursuing a specialized program on design and development of e-learning systems in India

WORKSHOPS

Workshop on Communicating Research with Broader Audiences: Policy and Decision-makers, Media, and Public

AWARE-AI NRT Program – Rochester Institute of Technology

Fulbright Enrichment and Leadership Seminar

Fulbright - University of California, Davis

REFERENCES

Will be furnished upon request